Ara Mesrobian Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ara Mesrobian Papers 1876-2011 1941-1994
MSS86360
Mesrobian, Ara, 1924-2019
2,800 items
8 containers plus 1 oversize
5 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Photographer and railroad enthusiast (railfan). Correspondence, railroad and trolley tickets and ticket books, railroad dining car menus, ephemera, and other material documenting mid-twentieth century rail travel, the operations of railway historical societies, and railfan subculture in the United States.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Ara Mesrobian were given to the Library of Congress in 2020 by Mesrobian's niece, Caroline Hickman. They were transferred to the Manuscript Division by the Prints and Photographs Division in 2020.
Related Material
The Prints and Photographs Division of the Library of Congress holds the Ara Mesrobian Railroad Photography Collection (see https://lccn.loc.gov/2020631257).
Transfers
Theater programs have been transferred to the Music Division where they are identified as part of the Ara Mesrobian Papers. Patrons are encouraged to contact the Music Division in advance of a research visit.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Ara Mesrobian are open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
Biographical Note
Ara Mesrobian was born August 7, 1924, in Washington, D.C. He attended Catholic University, graduating with a degree in electrical engineering in 1950 after serving in World War II in the Pacific Theater. He worked for the National Bureau of Standards for thirty years. In his free time, Mesrobian pursued his passion for photography and rail transportation, traveling widely to ride, photograph, and film trains. He was a member of the National Railway Historical Society (NRHS) for seventy years and was a founding member of the Potomac Chapter of the NRHS. He also participated in the Tractioneers, a Washington, D.C.-based organization devoted to trolleys and light-rail transportation. Mesrobian died June 18, 2019, in Chevy Chase, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ara Mesrobian (1924-2019) span the years 1876-2011, with the bulk of the material dating from 1941 to 1994. The collection documents Mesrobian’s deep interest in rail travel and provides insight into mid-twentieth century rail travel, the operations of railway historical societies, and railfan subculture in the United States.
The collection is primarily comprised of Mesrobian’s correspondence files from 1950 to 2011 and documents travel logistics, railway historical society events and activities, descriptions of trains, railways, and other transportation, and personal and business matters. The correspondence is filed in reverse chronological order within the folders. There is no correspondence from 1962. Mesrobian’s collections of railroad dining car menus, railroad, trolley, and streetcar tickets and ticket books, and other related ephemera also make up a significant portion of the collection. These materials are primarily from the United States and Canada, with a limited amount from Mesrobian’s European and Asian travels. There is also a significant amount of material related to railway historical society meetings and fan trips, including memorabilia associated with the last streetcar to travel over the original electric streetcar system in Washington, D.C. in 1962.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or material type.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Mesrobian, Ara, 1924-2019.
Subjects
Electric railroads--Washington (D.C.); Electric railroads.; Railfans--United States.; Railfans.; Railroad cars.; Railroad tickets.; Railroad trains.; Railroads--Asia.; Railroads--Canada.; Railroads--Dining-car service.; Railroads--Europe.; Railroads--Societies, etc.; Railroads--United States--History--20th century.; Railroads--United States--Societies, etc.; Railroads--United States.; Railroads.; Street-railroads--Washington (D.C.); Street-railroads.; Transportation--United States.
Places
Asia--Description and travel.; Canada--Description and travel.; Europe--Description and travel.; United States--Description and travel.
Occupations
Photographers.; Railfans.
Container List
- Biographical material, circa 1952 (Box 1)
- Clippings about transportation, 1949-1956 (Box 1)
- Clippings about transportation, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
- Clippings, Sacramento Northern Line, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1958, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1959, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1960, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1961, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1963, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1963-1964, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1965, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1966, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1967 (Box 3)
  - 1968 (Box 3)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - 1970, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1971 (Box 3)
  - 1972 (Box 3)
  - 1973 (Box 3)
  - 1974, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1975 (Box 4)
  - 1976 (Box 4)
  - 1977 (Box 4)
  - 1978 (Box 4)
  - 1979 (Box 4)
  - 1980 (Box 4)
  - 1981 (Box 4)
  - 1982 (Box 4)
  - 1983 (Box 4)
  - 1984 (Box 4)
  - 1985 (Box 4)
  - 1986 (Box 4)
  - 1987 (Box 4)
  - 1988 (Box 5)
  - 1989 (Box 5)
  - 1990 (Box 5)
  - 1991 (Box 5)
  - 1992 (Box 5)
  - 1993 (Box 5)
  - 1994 (Box 5)
  - 1995 (Box 5)
  - 1996 (Box 5)
  - 1997 (Box 5)
  - 1998 (Box 5)
  - 1999 (Box 5)
  - 2000-2011 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, Christmas card data (rosters, etc.), 1951-1994, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Correspondence, William C. Moore, 1919-1921, 1935 (Box 5)
- Ephemera (Box 5)
  - Baltimore and Annapolis Railroad Company notice, 1950 (Box OV1)
  - Central Electric Railfans Association, 20th Anniversary ribbon, 1958 (Box 5)
  - Interurban Trolley Service notice, 1953 (Box OV1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1951-1952, undated (Box 5)
  - Souvenir pins and tokens, 1948-1958, undated (Box 5)
  - Spanish railway stamps, 1958 (Box 5)
  - Virginia and Truckee Railroad Company, 1876-1897 (Box 5)
  - Waterloo, Cedar Falls, and Northern Railroad, 1951 (Box 5)
- Equipment notes and specifications (Box 5)
  - Arden Short Line Electric Railway, undated (Box 5)
  - Chesapeake and Ohio Railway, undated (Box 5)
  - "Electric Railways of the United States," Ohio Railway Museum, 1954 (Box 5)
  - "Guide to United States Railways" by Walter Martin, 1949 (Box 5)
  - "Pacific Great Eastern Railroad" by Fred D. Fellow, undated (Box 5)
  - "Progress: A Record of the Red Arrow Lines and the Area they Serve," circa 1943 (Box 5)
  - Washington and Old Dominion Railroad 100th anniversary, 1947 (Box 5)
  - Washington, Baltimore, and Annapolis lines, 1952 (Box 5)
- Fan trips (Box 5)
  - Capital Transit Company, 1948 (Box 5)
  - Capital Transit and Tractioneers "Gay Nineties" transit ride, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Cariboo Country Special trip, 1957 (Box 5)
  - D.C. Transit System streetcar, 1958-1962 (Box 5)
  - General Motors Aerotrain, undated (Box 5)
  - Rocky Mountain Railroad Club narrow gauge excursions, 1954-1955 (Box 6)
  - Tickets, 1941-1960 (Box 6)
- Map, Central Electric Traffic Association Railway Service (1912-1923), 1941 (Box OV1)
- Membership rosters, railway societies and clubs, 1955-2000, (3 folders) (Box 6)
- Menus, banquets, 1955, 1960, 1978 (Box 6)
- Menus, hotels, airlines, and boats, 1955-1994 (Box 6)
- Menus, railroad dining cars (Box 6)
  - possibly 1939 (Box 6)
  - 1949 (Box 6)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 6)
  - circa 1950-1969 (Box 6)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 6)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 6)
  - 1956-1957 (Box 6)
  - 1958 (Box 7)
  - 1959 (Box 7)
  - 1950s (Box 7)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 7)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 7)
  - 1970 (Box 7)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - 1974-1979 (Box 7)
  - 1981-1984 (Box 7)
  - 1992 (Box 7)
  - Undated (Box 7)
- Miscellany, 1949, undated (Box 7)
- National Railway Historical Society (Box 7)
  - Annual color slide contest awards, 1955-1969 (Box 7)
  - Annual convention, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Annual convention, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Annual convention programs, 1954-1955 (Box 7)
  - Annual convention programs and ephemera, 1950-1951 (Box 7)
  - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad special train, 1955 (Box 7)
  - Banquet menus, 1955-1958 (Box 7)
  - Constitution and bylaws, 1957 (Box 7)
  - Special trip to West Jefferson, N.C., 1956 (Box 7)
  - Sticker, undated (Box 7)
- Tickets (Box 8)
  - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad trips, 1951 (Box 8)
  - California, 1954-1958, undated (Box 8)
  - Canada, 1954-1958, undated (Box 8)
  - Connecticut, 1943, undated (Box 8)
  - Europe, 1959, undated (Box 8)
  - Illinois, 1951, undated (Box 8)
  - Iowa, 1951-1952, undated (Box 8)
  - Japan and Hong Kong, undated (Box 8)
  - Kansas, undated (Box 8)
  - Louisiana, undated (Box 8)
  - Maryland, 1943-1957, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Massachusetts, undated (Box 8)
  - Michigan, 1954-1955 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous tickets, undated (Box 8)
  - Missouri, possibly 1904, 1951 (Box 8)
  - New Jersey, undated (Box 8)
  - New York, 1939-1956 (Box 8)
  - New York to Montreal trip, 1951 August (Box 8)
  - North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee, undated (Box 8)
  - Ohio, 1941, 1951 (Box 8)
  - Oregon, undated (Box 8)
  - Pennsylvania, 1946-1957, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Société des Tramways de Constantinople, undated (Box 8)
  - Texas, 1948, undated (Box 8)
  - Virginia, 1913-1951, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Washington, D.C. metropolitan area, 1915-1956, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Wisconsin, 1946-1953, undated (Box 8)
- Washington Electric Railway Historical Society, bylaws and certificate of incorporation, 1949-1951 (Box 8)